Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是斯科特-曼利
A couple of weeks from now a spacecraft will streak across the skies of Mars,
几周后 一个航天器将在火星的天空中疾驰而过
decelerating from hyperbolic velocities protected by its heat shield
在热防护罩的保护下 从双曲线速度中减速前进
and containing the Mars 2020 rover now known as Perseverance.
并包含现在被称为 "毅力 "的火星2020探测器
Now I was lucky enough to actually visit JPL twice
现在 我很幸运地两次访问了JPL
and get to see Perseverance getting built in the clean room.
并能看到毅力号在无尘室中的建造
Obviously it was on the other side of a sheet of glass
很明显 它是在玻璃的另一面
but it was really cool to see this piece of hardware getting ready to go to Mars.
但看到这块硬件准备去火星 真的很酷
In many ways it's identical to Mars science laboratory better known as Curiosity
在许多方面 它与火星科学实验室（即好奇号）是一样的
which landed back in 2012 using the sky crane system.
它在2012年使用天车系统登陆
The sky crane is something that seemed a little crazy.
天空吊车是一个似乎有点疯狂的东西
At first we would probably use the word Kerbal
起初 我们可能会使用Kerbal这个词
except that back in 2012 Kerbal Space Program was only a year old
但在2012年 Kerbal Space Program只有一年的历史
and it hadn't quite infected the psyche of everyone that was into space stuff.
而且它还没有完全感染到每个人对太空事物的心理
The reasoning behind this design is that
这个设计背后的原因是
you can't build a parachute that is big enough to softly land a vehicle of this size and mass
你不可能造出一个足够大的降落伞来让这样大小和质量的飞行器软着陆
so you need rockets but rockets kick up a lot of dirt.
所以你需要火箭 但火箭会踢起很多土
So the sky crane allows the vehicle to be set down carefully
因此 空中起重机可以让飞行器小心翼翼地降落 并将其分开
detached and the sky crane can then fly away to its doom really.
脱离 然后天空起重机就可以飞走了 真的
And one of the things I'm most looking forward to is the fact that
我最期待的事情之一就是
this process will be documented by a multitude of cameras and microphones.
这个过程将被大量的摄像机和麦克风记录下来
And so I actually want to go back to Curiosity.
因此 我实际上想回到好奇号上
This is the image sequence captured by the Mars descent imager.
这是由火星下降成像仪拍摄的图像序列
It was a simple color camera.
它是一个简单的彩色相机
You'll see that I've corrected the shape of the frame to account for lens curvature.
你会看到 我已经纠正了画面的形状 以考虑到镜头的弯曲度
It was dumping jpeg images into an eight gigabyte buffer
它将jpeg图像转入一个八千兆字节的缓冲区
so it could take just enough images to get through the landing.
所以它可以拍摄足够多的图像来通过登陆
It would take images five times per second and it can compress those in real time.
它将每秒拍摄五次图像 它可以实时压缩这些图像
It couldn't take video.
它不能拍摄视频
It couldn't get audio.
它无法获取音频
But this was amazing to see this back in 2012.
但是在2012年看到这一点是令人惊讶的
It was the first time we'd really seen
这是我们第一次真正看到
an automated spacecraft in somewhat real time performing a landing on Mars.
一个自动化的航天器在某种程度上实时地在火星上进行着陆
I say real time these images came down days later
我说实时 这些图像是几天后才下来的
but when they were assembled it was really exciting.
但是当它们被组装起来的时候 真的很令人兴奋
So to just put some orientation on this to the right here is north.
因此 为了确定一些方向 右边是北方
To the left is the center of Gale Crater.
左边是盖尔陨石坑的中心
That black area is sand dunes.
那个黑色的区域是沙丘
And the thing about Gale Crater is it was probably filled with water
关于盖尔陨石坑的事情是它可能被水填满了
and it contains lots of sedimentary features
它包含许多沉积特征
and you can see channels and shorelines.
你可以看到渠道和海岸线
Now we're falling onto the parachute and about 1800 meters up from the surface
现在我们正落在降落伞上 在离地表大约1800米的地方
the parachute of the spacecraft will drop out and now it's under rocket thrust
航天器的降落伞将脱落 现在它处于火箭的推力之下
and you can actually see the vehicle banking to the the left
你实际上可以看到飞行器向左倾斜
and now it's banking over and looking out to the right.
现在它正向右倾斜并向右看去
This is just basically nulling out its horizontal velocity picking a landing site
这基本上是在抵消它的水平速度 选择一个着陆点
and now we start to get close to the surface.
现在我们开始接近表面了
It's slowing down and it will start deploying the vehicle.
它正在减速 将开始部署飞行器
So it's now less than 100 feet above the surface less than 30 meters.
所以它现在离地面不到100英尺 不到30米
There come the wheels.
轮子就在那里
It's now being lowered down towards the surface.
它现在正在向地面下降
You can't see much because of the debris getting thrown up
由于被抛起的碎片 你看不太清楚
but this is a lot less debris than would be thrown up if the rockets were attached to the vehicle itself.
但这比火箭与飞行器本身相连时抛出的碎片要少得多
And that's good because you don't want stuff blowing about.
这很好 因为你不希望东西被吹走
It would cause potentially cause damage to the rover.
它可能会导致对漫游者的损害
And now it's on the surface.
而现在它已经在表面了
That camera can still be used to look at stuff directly under the vehicle.
那台相机仍然可以用来观察车辆下面的东西
Now I actually discovered something pretty cool while trying to clean this thing up.
现在我在试图清理这个东西的时候 实际上发现了一些很酷的东西
And see this heat shield, this heat shield you can actually follow all the way down.
看到这个隔热罩 这个隔热罩你实际上可以一直跟下去
Now it obviously fades off into the distance.
现在 它显然已经消失在远处了
And gets very small.
而且变得非常小
But it's still very reflective.
但它仍然是非常反光的
And it stands out especially against the dark background of those dunes.
它在这些沙丘的黑暗背景下显得尤为突出
Or when the angle is right and it catches the the light.
或者当角度正确时 它能捕捉到光线
This is the last time that I honestly say that I can see the heat shield.
这是我最后一次诚实地说 我可以看到隔热罩
It's just between those two craters.
它就在那两个火山口之间
It catches the light for a few frames.
它捕捉到了几帧的光线
And you can see the pixels are just slightly brighter.
你可以看到像素稍微亮了一点
From there it's only a few seconds before the thing actually hits the ground
从那里开始 只有几秒钟的时间 这个东西就会真正地落到地面上
and we do actually see the impact.
而且我们确实看到了撞击
There's a big black splash that appears.
出现了一个巨大的黑色飞溅
And unfortunately it then moves out of frame
不幸的是 它随后移出了画面
so we don't get to see anything more after that.
所以在那之后我们没有看到更多的东西
But actually if you just ping pong the frames near the landing
但实际上 如果你把落地附近的帧打成乒乓状
then you actually can see the shadow coming up from the bottom
那么你实际上可以看到影子从底部上来了
like from the 7 o'clock mark and going in and out.
就像从7点钟的位置开始 进进出出
There's black spots where the shadow of the heat shield is just before it hits.
隔热罩的影子在它落地前有一些黑点
It probably has zero scientific value knowing this but I thought it was cool.
知道这些可能没有科学价值 但我认为这很酷
They have the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter
他们有火星勘测轨道器
and it was able to take images off the site the next day
它能够在第二天拍摄到该地点的图像
showing the landing site of
显示飞船的着陆点
the spacecraft, the heat shield, the parachute, the aeroshell, the sky crane.
航天器、隔热罩、降落伞、气囊、天车
All that stuff was scattered out over the area over a few kilometers.
所有这些东西都散落在几公里的区域内
And during the landing
而在着陆过程中
they actually slewed the camera on the Reconnaissance Orbiter over to higher angles.
他们实际上把侦察轨道器上的摄像机转到了更高的角度
So that they could actually catch the landing live
这样他们就能真正捕捉到降落的实况
and they picked out the parachute.
而他们挑出了降落伞
The vehicle aren't falling under the parachute.
车辆并没有在降落伞下坠落
Now of course the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter takes strips of data
当然 火星勘测轨道飞行器采取的是条状的数据
so this is part of a much larger image.
所以这是一张更大的图像的一部分
There is the thing under the parachute there.
那里是降落伞下的东西
But yeah down here this is actually where the landing occurred
但是 是的 在这里 这实际上是着陆的地方
so the camera is kind of looking down.
所以相机是往下看的
It's roughly 45 degree angle.
这大概是45度角
It says 42 degrees but the point is that it's coming down at an angle
它说是42度 但重点是它是以一个角度下来的
therefore you can actually estimate that
因此你实际上可以估计到
this is about two and a half kilometers up based upon the landing site being roughly here.
这大约是两公里半的高度 根据着陆点大致在这里
Stepping up a bit this is what the crater Gale Crater looks like from orbit.
再往上走一点 这是从轨道上看盖尔陨石坑的样子
And the Curiosity landed in the top left region here.
好奇号在这里的左上方区域着陆
That's to the northwest.
那是在西北部
You can see the big long black sand dune area there.
你可以看到那里的大的长的黑色沙丘区域
Zooming in a bit more,
再放大一点
you can see the channel right in the top left, the channel that flows in from the north
你可以看到左上方的通道 从北边流进来的通道
and beyond that channel you get an outflow area, a relatively flat area
而在这个通道之外 你会看到一个流出的区域 一个相对平坦的区域
and on the left side of this dune area
在这个沙丘区的左侧
you come to see a sort of gap where they plan to cross it onto Mount Sharp.
你会看到一个缺口 他们计划在那里穿越到夏普山
Okay so here we have a 3D model based upon satellite data from the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter
好的 所以这里我们有一个基于火星勘测轨道器的卫星数据的三维模型
and this shows the same landing site
这显示了同一个着陆点
and you can see a lot of the same features that we saw.
你可以看到很多与我们看到的相同的特征
I mean obviously you see that dune area.
我的意思是 很明显 你看到了那个沙丘区
You can see these shorelines
你可以看到这些海岸线
and actually if you slide this way you can see.
实际上 如果你这样滑动 你可以看到
This is obviously me sliding towards the north
这显然是我向北滑行
This is a channel that flowed into Gale Crater.
这是一条流入盖尔火山口的通道
It forms this alluvial flan.
它形成了这个冲积板
So the landing site is roughly about here.
所以着陆点大概在这里
And one thing you couldn't really tell from those cameras looking straight down was that
有一件事你无法从那些相机上看出来 那就是
there's actually a lot of relief in the terrain.
地形中实际上有很多的浮雕
If you look and I pan downwards you can actually see that to the south.
如果你看 我往下看 你实际上可以看到南部的情况
On the other side of these sand dunes is quite a substantial mountain.
在这些沙丘的另一边是一座相当大的山
This is about five kilometers tall fifteen thousand feet.
这大约有五公里高 一万五千英尺
And this is where Curiosity has been going for the last eight years or so
这就是好奇号在过去八年左右的时间里一直在走的地方
slowly making its way around these dunes.
慢慢地绕过这些沙丘
It basically headed down this way through this area here.
它基本上是以这种方式穿过这个区域
It had made a number of diversions and it's going around this.
它已经做了一些分流 它正在绕过这里
And going to be climbing up here.
并将在这里爬升
And eventually hoping to head up here into that mountain.
并最终希望从这里往上走 进入那座山
And as it goes up the side of this mountain,
当它爬上这座山的一侧时
you've got to realize that this is geology that's been laid down by sediment
你必须意识到这是由沉积物铺设的地质学
so as you go up, you're going to younger and younger terrain features.
所以当你往上走时 你会看到越来越年轻的地形特征
So you're getting a sort of a geological history of Mars.
所以你会得到一种火星的地质历史
And that's very good
而这是非常好的
because it can help you reconstruct the geological history of this planet.
因为它可以帮助你重建这个星球的地质历史
And this is what Curiosity sees of Mount Sharp.
这就是好奇号看到的夏普山
So it's a large mount in the middle of Gale Crater.
它是位于盖尔陨石坑中间的一个大山
It was formed during the impact
它是在撞击过程中形成的
when you have a large enough of energy large enough scales
当你有足够大的能量和足够大的尺度时
the ground actually behaves like a liquid
地面实际上表现得像一个液体
and it rebounds a little during the crater forming process.
它在火山口形成过程中会有一些反弹
And that is what stood for billions of years.
这就是几十亿年来的情况
And so there's all this geology up the side of the mountain that we want to investigate.
因此 在山的一侧有所有这些地质 我们想要调查
But to get there they had to take a bit of a circuitous route.
但是为了到达那里 他们不得不采取一个有点迂回的路线
They had to initially go to the south west around all that black sand.
他们最初不得不绕过那些黑沙 向西南方向前进
So they could then turn and cut through a gap into the actual mountainous region.
这样他们就可以转弯 从一个缺口切入实际的山区
Now of course translating maps and images to an idea of what the Mars is like is hard
当然 将地图和图像转化为对火星的概念是很难的
which is why I find it great that
这就是为什么我发现它很好
there's a few sites that NASA has gone and essentially constructed 3d environments for.
有几个地方 美国宇航局已经去了 并基本上构建了3D环境
This is Dingle Gap.
这是Dingle Gap
Yes it's named after an Australian site. There you go.
是的 它是以澳大利亚的一个地点命名的 你去那里吧
And it's located where a bunch of sand dunes are.
它位于一堆沙丘的地方
So yeah this is all literally running in my browser.
所以是的 这都是在我的浏览器上运行的
So I'm just dragging this around and lets me view various things.
所以我只是拖动这个 让我查看各种东西
If you want to figure out say what this looks like
如果你想弄清楚 比如说这个看起来像什么
you just click on it puts a flag in it.
你只需点击它 就可以在里面插上一个旗子
And you can actually see where that corresponds to in the various navigation cameras.
而你实际上可以看到这在各种导航相机中对应的位置
They have a bunch of different sites in here.
他们在这里有一堆不同的网站
It's not a huge number.
这不是一个巨大的数字
I guess it takes a lot of time to do all the photogrammetry.
我想这需要大量的时间来做所有的摄影测量
This is a standing looking at this very interesting wall here.
这是一个站在这里看这个非常有趣的墙
And again you can just click on it and find the various parts.
你可以再次点击它 找到各个部分
This is the Kimberley.
这是金伯利
These are all north office.
这些都是北面的办公室
So if you look at the various points,
所以如果你看一下各个点
this is still north of the sand dunes.
这仍然是沙丘的北部
If I zoom out and over there is the sand dunes still getting in our way.
如果我放大 那边是沙丘 仍然妨碍着我们
But again click and you shall see the various images.
但再次点击 你将看到各种图像
By 2018 they were had crossed the dunes and were starting to climb the mountain.
到2018年 他们已经越过沙丘 开始爬山了
And one of the first things they did was
他们首先做的一件事是
when they found a ridge they turned around and took a complete panorama
当他们发现一个山脊时 他们转过身来 拍了一张完整的全景图
which showed where they had been all the places they had analyzed.
这显示了他们曾经去过的所有地方 他们已经分析过了
All the sites they had drilled, photographed
所有他们钻探过的地方 拍下的照片
and subject to all the instruments that Mars Science Laboratory brought with them.
以及火星科学实验室带来的所有仪器
And after seeing their opportunity
在看到他们的机会后
they found a way to pick their way across the dunes
他们找到了一条穿过沙丘的方法
being always mindful of how spirit ended up stuck in a sand trap before ultimately failing.
始终注意到精神是如何在最终失败之前陷入沙坑的
Of course while crossing you've got some amazing photos of these sand dunes like the patterns there.
当然 在穿越的时候 你已经得到了这些沙丘的一些惊人的照片 比如那里的图案
Pretty darn unreal.
相当不真实
Teally glad that they actually include the scaling on here.
我很高兴他们真的在这里加入了缩放功能
I mean this is what happens when you leave sand to get blown around and have all the dynamics work on.
我的意思是 这就是当你让沙子被吹来吹去 并让所有的动态工作发生的情况
It's black basalt based sand which there may have been a whole lot more of this in the past
这是以黑色玄武岩为基础的沙子 在过去可能有很多这样的情况
but even then you get these big dunes that are migrating across the bottom of the crater.
但即使如此 你也可以看到这些大沙丘在火山口的底部移动
Now obviously Curiosity has been sciencing the heck out of everywhere as it traverses this landscape.
现在很明显 好奇号在穿越这一地貌时 已经对所有地方进行了科学考察
And this image shows us all the sites that they took drill samples from
这张图片向我们展示了他们采集钻探样本的所有地点
and one thing I want you to notice is that
我想让你注意到的一件事是
the names are all sort of appropriate to each other
我想让你注意的是 这些名字都是相互对应的
so as they move down the themes are changing
所以当他们向下移动时 主题也在变化
and right down the bottom
而在底部
those last two rows are all... once they cross the dunes onto Mount Sharp
最后两行都是......一旦他们越过沙丘来到夏普山
those are all places in Scotland.
这些都是苏格兰的地方
So they have basically decided once they crossed on to Mount Sharp
所以他们基本上已经决定一旦他们越过夏普山
that is Scotland and they've been there for the last thousand days.
那就是苏格兰 他们已经在那里呆了一千天了
They're now crossing into a new region which is going to have a French theme.
他们现在要穿越到一个新的地区 这个地区将有一个法国主题
And so for climbing Mount Sharp
因此 为了攀登夏普山
they're moving through a region right now which is called the clay unit
他们现在正穿过一个区域 这个区域被称为粘土单元
that's because it has spectra that implies there were clay minerals here.
这是因为它的光谱意味着这里有粘土矿物
Very interesting if you're of course looking for ancient water.
如果你要寻找古代的水 那就非常有趣了
They're going to have to go up through this channel
他们将不得不穿过这条通道
that has been cut down the side of the mountain through the sulphate unit.
从山的一侧切入 穿过硫酸盐单元
Again the evidence from orbit points to high sulfate levels in these rocks.
来自轨道的证据再次表明这些岩石中的硫酸盐含量很高
But yeah this is a channel
但是 这是一个通道
that has been cut through it by a water flow from higher up Mount Sharp down the side
被从夏普山更高处流下的水切割成的通道
and so this is great because not only is it an easier path
所以这很好 因为它不仅是一个更容易的路径
but it also has cut down through the layers giving access to geology
而且它还穿过了层层叠叠的岩石 使人们能够看到地质情况
which they might not be visible in other locations.
在其他地方可能无法看到
So as of right now this is the most recent panorama that's come down.
所以到现在为止 这是最近下来的全景图
This is from january and it's still in the Scottish region
这是从1月开始的 它仍然在苏格兰地区
but they're now moving headed into the french region of Mars.
但他们现在正向火星的法国地区前进
But the vehicle is powered by a radioisotope thermoelectric generator.
但该车是由放射性同位素热电发电机提供动力
Its lifetime is limited.
它的寿命是有限的
The plutonium that powers that has a half-life of like 80 odd years.
为其提供动力的钚的半衰期为80年左右
And as this power decays they're going to have to start taking steps to reduce the power usage.
随着这种动力的衰减 他们将不得不开始采取措施 减少动力的使用
It's not just the RTG because that charges batteries
这不仅仅是RTG 因为它为电池充电
and the batteries also degrade over time.
而电池也会随着时间的推移而退化
So they have to take all this into account
所以他们必须考虑到所有这些
but most likely this thing is going to have a limited life.
但最有可能的是 这个东西将有一个有限的寿命
And it's really a question of
而这实际上是一个问题
how far up it gets Mount Sharp before it has to take its leave.
在它不得不离开之前 它在夏普山上走了多远
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是斯科特-曼利 飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]